<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>RailsConf2008 on Leonardo Borges</title>
    <link>http://leonardoborges.com/tags/railsconf2008/</link>
    <description>Recent content in RailsConf2008 on Leonardo Borges</description>
    <generator>Hugo</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Tue, 09 Sep 2008 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <atom:link href="http://leonardoborges.com/tags/railsconf2008/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>railsconf europe 2008 impressions and highlights</title>
      <link>http://leonardoborges.com/writings/2008/09/09/railsconf-europe-2008-impressions-and-highlights/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 09 Sep 2008 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://leonardoborges.com/writings/2008/09/09/railsconf-europe-2008-impressions-and-highlights/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&#xA;I&#39;m back in Madrid again after the RailsConf and I think it&#39;s time to say something about it. :)&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;First off, the infrastructure provided by the conference was really great. The rooms, WiFi connection, food...  Really well organized.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;Now to the sessions, highlights:&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Tutorials (Tuesday)&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br&gt;- &lt;a href=&#34;http://nealford.com/downloads/Ford-Farley_Meta_programming_ruby-tutorial.pdf&#34;&gt;Meta-programming Ruby for fun and profit&lt;/a&gt; (Neal Ford, Patrick Farley)&lt;br&gt;The old and good techniques that made Ruby so powerful. Here Neal and Patrick walked us through the main tricks to meta programming like open classes - and conditionally open them - , dynamically define methods, sending messages to objects and how Ruby can help test your Java code in a much easier way.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;I&#39;ve put the link to the slides but honestly I don&#39;t think they&#39;re too much useful without the talking.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Sessions (Wednessday)&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br&gt;- EC2, MapReduce and Distributed processing (&lt;a href=&#34;http://railspikes.com&#34;&gt;Jonathan Dahl&lt;/a&gt;)&lt;br&gt;Jonathan explained the theory behind &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Mapreduce&#34;&gt;MapReduce&lt;/a&gt; using very simple ruby examples, providing the basics on how to distribute and paralelize tasks accross multiple machines.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;He also introduced &lt;a href=&#34;http://hadoop.apache.org/core/&#34;&gt;Hadoop&lt;/a&gt;, a platform built in Java that &#34;lets one easily write and run     applications that process vast amounts of data&#34;. What I liked the most was the simplicity he explained this subject. As of today, his presentation is not available online. Stay tuned as I&#39;m gonna update this post with the links, as soon as they&#39;re available.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Sessions (Thursday)&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br&gt;- &lt;a href=&#34;http://nealford.com/downloads/conferences/canonical/Neal_Ford-Debugging_and_Testing_the_Web_Tier.zip&#34;&gt;Debugging &amp;amp; Testing the Web Tier&lt;/a&gt; (&lt;a href=&#34;http://nealford.com&#34;&gt;Neal Ford&lt;/a&gt;)&lt;br&gt;If you&#39;ve been concerned about testing your app&#39;s web tier lately, this presentation would probably not show you anything new. Neal talks about the need to debug and test javascript behaviour accross multiple browsers, using tools like &lt;a href=&#34;http://getfirebug.com/&#34;&gt;Firebug&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.jsunit.net/&#34;&gt;JSUnit&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&#34;http://selenium.openqa.org/&#34;&gt;Selenium&lt;/a&gt;. If you have no idea about what these tools are, please stop now and go evaluate them!&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;We are pretty concerned about testing on my actual job, but selenium tests can be a pain sometimes - a.k.a extremely slow. And what ends up happening is that they are forgotten. Developers only run the test suite if it&#39;s not painful and it&#39;s lightning fast. Here&#39;s is where the highlight for this session comes: &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.thefrontside.net/crosscheck&#34;&gt;CrossCheck&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;The idea is to be able to test your javascript code accross multiple browsers without the need to launch them. In fact, you don&#39;t even need a browser installed. The negative point is that it&#39;s kinda fallen behind because now you can only test older versions of browsers. But since the project is getting a lot of traction, I&#39;m pretty sure this will be solved soon.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Conclusion&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;My overall impression of the other sessions I attended is that some speakers just didn&#39;t have time to properly prepare themselves, what made me think this years&#39;s RailsConf wasn&#39;t all that I expected.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;But I also met interesting people and after all one of the key points in a conference is networking. :)&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;Definitely worth it though. And that&#39;s why I took the time to provide this highlights.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;c u soon&#xA;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
