<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Productivity on Leonardo Borges</title>
    <link>http://leonardoborges.com/tags/productivity/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Productivity on Leonardo Borges</description>
    <generator>Hugo</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Tue, 12 May 2020 08:31:15 +1000</lastBuildDate>
    <atom:link href="http://leonardoborges.com/tags/productivity/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>Be Bored</title>
      <link>http://leonardoborges.com/writings/2020/05/12/be-bored/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 12 May 2020 08:31:15 +1000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://leonardoborges.com/writings/2020/05/12/be-bored/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Recently I wrote an internal blog post at work titled &lt;em&gt;On the traps of working from home&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;While the content isn&amp;rsquo;t new it was triggered by the recent events around COVID-19 and the fact that all of a sudden the whole company was working from home, distributed across multiple timezones.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;I was worried that we may default to having more meetings instead of better communication and writing this post was my attempt to share how I tend to deal with distractions.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>how do you keep yourself focused</title>
      <link>http://leonardoborges.com/writings/2009/06/08/how-do-you-keep-yourself-focused/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 08 Jun 2009 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://leonardoborges.com/writings/2009/06/08/how-do-you-keep-yourself-focused/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&#xA;This is basically a compilation of a few tools/habits that I use to keep focused and at a high level of productivity when working alone. Works great for me and I hope there are useful tips for you as well.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;dl&gt; &lt;dt&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Music&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/dt&gt; &lt;dd&gt;This is one of my favorites. When working alone I hate having noisy people around, which happens quite often if you work in an open office space like me. - It is great for pair programming but I find it inefficient otherwise. Thus, I came up with the term &lt;strong&gt;the Heavy Metal effect&lt;/strong&gt;. Ok, just fit your favorite music genre there but the important thing is that it must act as a barrier to the outside world. It won&#39;t work if you put something new and start babbling the lyrics!&lt;/dd&gt; &lt;dt&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Password Manager&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/dt&gt; &lt;dd&gt;In my day to day I have a number of web sites open like API documents, programming related groups, email... There are also the ones you open a few times a day like the company bug tracker, review board and etc. I find that having a password manager, in my case &lt;a href=&#34;https://lastpass.com/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;LastPass&lt;/a&gt;, saves a lot of time. The big advantage of it over similar tools like 1Password is that it works on mac, linux or windows. It&#39;s just a firefox plugin.&lt;/dd&gt; &lt;dt&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Multiple Workspaces&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/dt&gt; &lt;dd&gt;Probably the most obvious item on this list to developers but I&#39;s never too much to reinforce it. Multiple workspaces are great. And they are available in whatever platform you happen to be locked in. In my case, I split my environment in at least 3 workspaces:&lt;br&gt;-&lt;strong&gt;Development&lt;/strong&gt; - where I keep things like my IDE, Browser and Terminal&lt;br&gt;-&lt;strong&gt;Documentation&lt;/strong&gt; - where I keep API documents, tutorials and related stuff&lt;br&gt;-&lt;strong&gt;Communication&lt;/strong&gt; - where I have my email, both personal and business, twitter and etc. This allows me to easily set a time per day to do each of my stuff without having noise from things that aren&#39;t important to what I&#39;m focusing in that very moment. &lt;/dd&gt; &lt;dt&gt;&lt;strong&gt;App Launcher&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/dt&gt; &lt;dd&gt;A must! On Mac I use &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.versiontracker.com/dyn/moreinfo/macosx/22549&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;QuickSilver&lt;/a&gt; and on Linux, &lt;a href=&#34;http://do.davebsd.com/release.shtml&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Gnome Do&lt;/a&gt;. I won&#39;t say much here. If you don&#39;t use some sort of application launcher, do yourself a favor, stop reading and install one. You have no idea of how comfortable and time saver they are.&lt;/dd&gt; &lt;dt&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Batch tasks&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/dt&gt; &lt;dd&gt;Maybe this wasn&#39;t the best title but I couldn&#39;t think of anything better.&lt;br&gt;As a result of having a communication workspace that I use a few times a day, I find stuff that I&#39;m interested in but don&#39;t have the time to dig at the moment. So I need a way to queue that and read later when I&#39;m home. The tools of the trade in this case are &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.twitter.com&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Twitter&lt;/a&gt; + &lt;a href=&#34;http://blog.evernote.com/2009/04/14/evernote_twitter/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Evernote&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;br&gt;Evernote is roughly a to-do manager. And since they released their Twitter integration it&#39;s been dead easy to queue those things I talked about earlier. Just send a direct message to evernote and the item gets added instantly. &lt;/dd&gt; &lt;/dl&gt;Now, what about you? What works for you?&#xA;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
